Guide to the Alva I. Cox Jr. Papers
Yale University Divinity School Library
- Social Awareness / Social Justice, Series IX
  - Issues in the U.S.A.
    - "Looking Back Looking Forward" (Aleutian/Pribilof Island Association); This filmstrip and cassette package was also created in response to the Land Claim Settlement in Alaska. Filmstrips: 3 (2 volumes, one volume has 2 copies) audio cassette: 2 copies (Box 126)
    - "Alaska Land Claims Act Audio Tapes"; These interviews led to the making of "Early Days Ago" and "On Our Own." audio cassette: 10 volumes (Box 115)
    - "Echoes of the Revolution" (VHS), 1976 (Box 59)
      This film was produced for the Ecumenical Task Force on the Religious Observance of the Nation's Bicentennial and for the Department of Education for Mission of the National Council of Churches. Approximately 26 minutes long, it was filmed in a strip mining area in southeastern Ohio and in industrial sections of Cleveland. It features ordinary people in unscripted and unrehearsed conversation responding to the question of whether, two hundred years after the American Revolution, freedom and justice are realities in their lives and in the life of America.
    - "Echoes of the Revolution" (16mm: 2 copies) (Box OV6)
    - "Echoes of the Revolution" (Beta), 1976; 1 (Box 59, Item barcode 39002098995377)
    - "Echoes of the Revolution" Utilization Guide: 4 copies (Box OV6, Box 59)
    - "The Eighth Fire"; This film is about present-day Native American issues, such as treaty disputes over hunting and fishing, as well as disputes about reservation lands. (VHS), No date; 1 (Box 59, Item barcode 39002098995385)
    - "Native American Issues"; These are interviews with Native Americans (mostly in the Scottsbluff/Gering area of Nebraska) about issues of hunger, welfare, and discrimination. (audio cassette: 3 volumes) (Box 115)
    - "Rural Crisis: A Call for Justice and Action"; This is about the economic crisis faced by farmers. Final Version (VHS), May 5, 1987; 1 (Box 59, Item barcode 39002098995393)
    - "Rural Crisis: A Call for Justice and Action" (U-matic: 2 copies, one of which is the Edited Master), No date; 2 (Box 80, Item barcode 39002098996144)
    - "Rural Crisis: A Call for Justice and Action" Resource materials (audio cassette;interview with Phil Givens) (Box 116)
    - "A Void of Desolation?"; A filmstrip about toxic waste and its impact on our quality of life. (filmstrip; audio cassette: 2 copies) (Box 121)
  - Issues Abroad
    - "Bangladesh Flood" (Peter Williams w/CC); Raw footage of the Bangladesh flood. (VHS), No date; 1 (Box 60, Item barcode 39002129368784)
    - "Killing A Dream" (Anders Hilsen); This film is about violence committed by police, military, and other groups in South Africa and Mozambique. (VHS) (Box 60)
    - Nepal and Cambodia (photo sets: 7) (Box 117)
    - Cambodia and GBGM Center (photo sets: 4) (Box 118)
    - Nelson Mandela, New Mexico aerials, choir, etc. (photo sets: 4 plus negatives) (Box 119)
    - "Serge Savarof, Looking Forward Conference" ("Recollections of Youth in Nikolski") (audio cassette) (Box 116)
    - "Somalia, Senegal, and other parts of Africa"; Interviews about missionaries helping refugees and natives in Africa. (audio cassette) (Box 116)
    - "South Africa Report" ("South Africa Now," Newsreel One ) (VHS), Jun 1986; 1 (Box 60, Item barcode 39002098995443)
      This film is about intimidation by police in South Africa against native Africans, such as the police imprisoning and abusing teenage boys, and about peaceful protest against the violence.
    - "South Africa Report--Chicago" (U-matic S), Nov. 5, 1986 (Box 80)
- Spanish Films, Series X
  - "Abramos Nuestras Puertas ('We Open Our Doors')"; This film relates to alcoholism, drug addiction, and use of tobacco. (VHS), No date; 1 (Box 60, Item barcode 39002098995401)
  - "De Mujer A Mujer" (trans: "Woman to Woman") (VHS), May 16, 1986 (Box 60)
    A planning committee of women from a local chapter of the UMC in San Antonio, TX, plan a program for the women in their church. The program is taken from the book Mujeres Forjando un Mundo ("Women Forging a World"). It centers on how women face change, and how they cope with it. The first part of the video is of the women in committee discussing and planning the program. The second half is the program itself.
  - "De Mujer A Mujer del Libro de Recursos" (U-matic), 1986; 1 (Box 81, Item barcode 39002098996474)
- Individuals, Series XI
  - "General Secretary's Mission Lecture Series: Dr. Wesley Ariarajah"; Dr. Ariarajah speaks about the future of mission evangelism from an ecumenical perspective. (VHS), Dec. 1998; 1 (Box 60, Item barcode 39002098995435)
  - "Malcolm Blackburn memorial"; A tape from the memorial service for Rev. Malcolm Blackburn, an Episcopal priest who was a leader in the ecumenical movement. (audio cassette) (Box 116)
  - "Dr. Eugene C. Blake"; This program is part of an ABC Bicentennial celebration series called Directions: Conscience of America. This particular program is an interview about the ecumenical movement with Dr. Eugene C. Blake, former president of the NCC. The video is in black and white, and looks older than 1976, the year of the bicentennial. (Beta) (Box 60)
  - "Dr. Kenyon C. Burke--A Tribute" (VHS), Dec. 13, 1993; 1 (Box 60, Item barcode 39002098995427)
    A tribute to Burke through video footage of him in action (such as his work in social justice issues), as well as interviews with him.
  - "Will Campbell"; Interview with a Baptist minister in Mississippi who is accepting of KKK members (but not necessarily of the views of the KKK) (audio cassette) (Box 116)
  - "Jimmy Carter Special" (Beta), No date; 1 (Box 72, Item barcode 39002098996003)
  - "Alva Irwin Cox, Jr."; Photograph, biography, obituary, and funeral program of Al Cox, Jr. (Box 157)
  - "16 and 17"; Interview with Ivan Delk, a UCC minister who is the national chairperson for Project Equality. (audio cassette) (Box 116)
  - Ed Espy / Arie Brouwer Memorial"; This video consists of two memorials for former presidents of the NCC. The first half is that of Ed Espy, which has a brief history of him as well as one of his last interviews. The second is that of Arie Brouwer, consisting of his acceptance speech overlaid with video. (VHS; picture quality is poor.), Nov. 9, 1993 (Box 24)
  - "Tom Fassett"; Raw footage of an interview with Tom Fassett of the UMC in Alaska. (U-matic S: 4 volumes), July 31, 1986 (Box 109–110)
  - "Archbishop Iakovos--Faith and Order Endowment Fund"; Raw footage from the dinner honoring Archbishop Iakovos and his efforts in ecumenism, such as through the Faith and Order program. Final version (VHS - VTC), May 22, 1995
  - "Archbishop Iakovos--Faith and Order Endowment Fund" (Beta) (Box 61)
  - "Archbishop Iakovos--Faith and Order Endowment Fund" Resource materials (VHS: 4 volumes) (Box 61)
  - "Bola Iga"; Raw footage from an interview with Bola Iga, a lawyer from Nigeria who was a coordinator of the college student movement and talked at various colleges. (VHS: 2 volumes), Sep. 26, 1990 (Box 61)
  - Bola Ige - interview re. African student movement - volume 1 (U-matic SP), 1990; 1 (Box 112, Item barcode 39002098996219)
  - Bola Ige - interview re. African student movement - volume 2, 1990; 1 (Box 112, Item barcode 39002098996227)
  - "Dr. Ron Meyers--NCCC #1"; Raw footage of a speech by Dr. Ron Meyers on health justice issues (especially health care policies). (VHS - VTC), Nov. 14, 1991 (Box 27)
  - "Dr. Ron Meyers--NCCC #1" (Beta) (Box 62)
  - "Mission 21"; Raw footage of an interview with theologian Mercy Oduyoye about the coming of the year 2000 and Christianity in Africa. (VHS: 3 volumes), June 1, 1998 (Box 62)
  - "Church World Service #21 Lecture: Dalee Sambo"; Raw footage of Dalee Sambo speaking about attempts to bring concerns about recognition of tribal governments in Alaska to the attention of state and federal government. (U-matic), April 23, 1986 (Box 81)
  - "Church World Service #21 Lecture: Dalee Sambo" (U-matic S) (Box 112)
  - "Ground of Faith with Andrew Young--CBS News"; A religious special by CBS TV about Rev. Andrew Young, U.S. representative to the U.N. (VHS), Sep. 3, 1978; 1 (Box 62, Item barcode 39002098995849, Box 82)
- Other Topics, Series XII
  - Miscellaneous
    - "Sample Reel"; Perhaps a kind of 'video resume' for Synesthetics, Inc. It includes excerpts from: 1) "Signs of Change" for CWS; 2) "Mission 2000" for the National Division General Board of Global Ministries, UMC; 3) "Mozambique Report" for CWS; 4) "A Tradition of Excellence" for Alaska Children's Services. (U-matic) (Box 63)
    - "Bioenergetic Group Therapy" (slide carousel) (Box 122)
    - "Bioenergetic Analysis" (slide carousel) (Box 123)
    - "Environment -- Negative"; This box of slides contains images of the harmful effects industries can have on the environment. It includes a basic guide to the slides on the inside of the lid. (Box OV10)
    - "To Belong Again"; This is a 17-minute film in color, produced during Klingberg Family Centers' 75th year. (VHS: 2 copies), 1978; 2 (Box 154, Item barcode 39002098996466, Box 156)
      The film focuses on the Centers at work today, and also describes how the original "Children's Home" was begun by John Eric Klingberg, D.D. Various KFC alumni, including Barbara McCann, current Board of Trustee member, appear in the film.
    - "To Belong Again" (16 mm) (Box OV4)
    - "To Belong Again" user guide: 3 copies (Box OV4, Box 150)
    - YWCA 1981 ("It Takes All Kinds"); Three commercials for the YWCA. (VHS: 2 copies), 2 (Box 150, Item barcode 39002098996433, Box 151)
    - YWCA 1981 ("It Takes All Kinds") (16 mm: 2 copies) (Box OV4)
    - "YWCA"; Interviews about the YWCA. (audio cassette: 2 volumes) (Box 115)
    - YWCA slide carousel (Box 120)
    - "UMC: Swaziland Choir" (MP L60: 2 volumes), June 29, 1987 (Box 141)
    - "J.E.A. film recording"; This is an audio recording of a film about jazz. (audio cassette) (Box 116)
    - "Love" (August 2000); This is an artistic film about love, shown through black and white photos and accompanied by music. (VHS), No date; 1 (Box 62, Item barcode 39002098995856)
    - "Love" (16 mm) (Box OV4)
    - "Work" (Union Seminary); This is an artistic film about work. It is similar in style to "Love" with its use of music to accompany black and white photos. (VHS), No date; 1 (Box 62, Item barcode 39002098995872)
    - "Work" (16 mm) (Box OV4)
  - Re. other cultures
    - "St. Lawrence / Nome Dancers"; Raw footage of Native Alaskan dancers, part 1 (U-matic S), No date; 1 (Box 112, Item barcode 39002098996235)
    - "St. Lawrence / Nome Dancers"; Raw footage of Native Alaskan dancers, part 2 (U-matic S), No date; 1 (Box 112, Item barcode 39002098996243)
    - "St. Lawrence / Nome Dancers"; Raw footage of Native Alaskan dancers, part 3 (U-matic S), No date; 1 (Box 112, Item barcode 39002098996250)
    - "CWS St. Lawrence Dancers #2"; Raw footage with time code of Native Alaskan dancers. (U-matic), Oct. 2, 1986 (Box 82)
    - "Israel" (slide carousel) (Box 124)
    - "VEJEN"; This film is about Buddhism in Burma. (Carousel Films, Inc., produced by Elsebet Kjolbye) (VHS), 1971; 1 (Box 62, Item barcode 39002098995864)
      A narrator reads Buddhist teachings (in English) while a Buddhist monk is shown enacting these teachings within the community. A little boy accompanies the monk, and he then becomes the lead in a play telling about the story of the prince who became the Buddha. Every boy in Burma becomes the young prince once in his life. He must wear the robes of a Buddhist monk for at least the following week; but sometimes he chooses to wear it longer, whether it be for a month, a year, or perhaps for the rest of his life.
    - "VEJEN" (16 mm) (Box OV4)
- Kent State, Series XIII
  - Kent State: May 1970 (final version) (VHS), 1972; 1 (Box 129, Item barcode 39002098996326)
    This film recreates the events at Kent State University leading up to the shootings in which members of the Ohio National Guard killed 4 students and injured 9 others. E.G. Marshall narrates a detailed chronology of the actions triggered by President Nixon's announcement of the invasion of Cambodia. The live action takes place in actual campus locations, but the film cuts to still photos taken by the many photographers to document each assertion. These photos help reconstruct the events accurately and to assess the various, contradictory interpretations of what happened that day.
  - Kent State: May 1970 (16 mm: 3 copies) (Box 129)
  - Kent State: May 1970 User Guide: 2 volumes (Box 129)
  - Kent State resource materials (TRK and PIX rolls: 55 volumes) (Box OV11–OV14, Box 135–140)
  - Kent State resource materials (audio reels: 5 volumes) (Box 134)
  - Kent State slides (221) (Box 133)
  - Kent State slides (161) (Box 132)
  - Description of camera shots (written) (Box 130)
  - Narration script read by E.G. Marshall, and fact sheet (written) (Box 130)
  - Kent State Aftermath: newspaper articles, proposal for a TV hour special, correspondence. (Box 130)
  - Petitions for federal grand jury, "Prelude to Murder", newspaper articles, misc. letters (Box 130)
  - Congressional record materials and responses to Congress findings (Box 130)
  - Original newspaper articles about Attny General John Mitchell closing case (Box 130)
  - Article "The Truth About Kent State." (Box 130)
  - Kent State correspondence (rental receipts, etc.) (Box 130)
  - Kent State Alumni Publication June 1970 (one month after the shooting) (Box 130)
  - An Appeal for Justice, June 21, 1971 (Box 130)
  - Newspapers, magazine, and a collection of poems by Kent State locals. (Box 130)
  - Kent State paperwork (mostly receipts) (Box 130)
  - Letters regarding 1972 Miami Beach Coalition, response to Mitchell (Box 130)
  - Newspaper clippings on Grand Jury, on Peter Davies' donation to Yale, and Davies' book reviewed. (Box 130)
  - Original newspaper clippings (Box 130)
  - The appeals to the Sixth Circuit U.S. Court of Appeals and the U.S. Supreme Court (Box 130)
  - Kent State business (contracts for use of the film) (Box 131)
  - Expense Report (Box 131)
  - Original paperwork from making of film, scripts, Cox's personal notes, hand edited script (Box 131)